בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Yeah, so today's daf is דף כ"ז, daf
kaf zayin, 27. We pick up at the very, very bottom really
the last two words of כ"ו עמוד ב'. kaf vav amud bet.
And we're dealing now with the... we're not in the 18 things
of בית שמאי ובית הלל, Beit Shammai u-Beit Hillel, we're going to
get back to that, but we are now in the fact that
a list was quoted about earlier תקנות, takanot, and two תקנות: takanot:
one about the glassware is מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, and the other
that the land of non-Jews is considered טמא, tamei, and that was
made very early from יוסי בן יועזר איש צרדה Yose ben Yoezer
Ish Tzereda and יוסי בן... and who was it? and יוסי בן
יועזר איש צרדה and יוסי בן יוחנן איש ירושלים. Yose ben Yochanan
Ish Yerushalayim. So now we are dealing with the issue of the
glassware. And the question is, why did the חז"ל Chazal decide to
say the glassware would become טמא? tamei? Now you can't just say,
well, maybe they applied it to all vessels, because there are vessels
that biblically are טהור tahor and remain טהור, tahor, like those made
out of stone for example. So why here did they feel that
glassware had to be טמא? tamei? And they say because it was
very similar to earthenware; it was made out of sand. And that
means that the assumption is going to be that it's going to
have a status like כלי חרס, kli cheres, like earthenware. Now one
of the primary issues about earthenware is that you can't take it
to the מקוה. mikveh. So the question was what do you do
with the fact that glassware it's clear you can take it to
the מקוה? mikveh? So the גמרא Gemara says, well, that's a special
exception. Really glassware you wouldn't be able to take to a מקוה;
mikveh; the only way it could become טהור tahor is by breaking
it, by making a hole in it. So what's the case therefore
by glassware that you can take it to a מקוה? mikveh? That's
a special case where the glass had a hole in it. So
it has a hole, it stops being earthenware, it starts, stops being
a כלי, kli, because the general rule is that a כלי kli
that has a hole in it, you know, a certain size hole,
stops being a כלי, kli, כלי חרס. kli cheres. And then it
became a כלי kli by filling that hole with lead. So therefore,
because it was filled with lead, the lead made it a כלי,
kli, and therefore in that case, according to רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
position, it has the status of a metal vessel and can go
into the מקוה. mikveh. But normal glassware would be considered to be
like what do you call it, would be considered to be like
חרס cheres and cannot go into the מקוה. mikveh. Now the גמרא
Gemara picks up with that question, whether glassware really has the status
of כלי חרס. kli cheres. So let's take a look. אלא מעתה
Ella me'atah says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, לא ליטמא מגבן.
lo litamei migaban.
So the most obvious issue about pottery ware, earthenware, is not that
it can go to the מקוה mikveh or not go to the
מקוה, mikveh, that is one difference, but the most obvious issue for
those who are in the world of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah is
how they become טמא: tamei: that normal vessels become טמא tamei when
you touch any part of them, whereas pottery only becomes טמא tamei
when something is on the inside; it doesn't even have to touch
the inside, it has to be in the inside. So if you
have a earthenware cup and you touch the outside or the bottom,
nothing would happen. If you suspended something in the air of the
inside of the cup, it would become טמא. tamei. So the question
is, if that's true, if glass is considered to be like earthenware,
it should not become טמא tamei when it touches the back. How
do we know that's not true? So it says the following: אלמה
תנן, Alamma tnan, why have we taught in a משנה Mishnah in
כלים, Kelim, כלי חרס וכלי
נתר, kli cheres ve-kli nether, earthenware and נתר nether (how did they
translate נתר, nether, by the way? Is anybody looking at an English?)
Natron. Natron, yeah, that's exactly what I what I thought too. What
does that, what's natron?
It says it's
one of the three different minerals: natron, alum, and chalk.
By sodium carbonate.
Okay, so can you tell us anything, Charlie? No. Anyway, so it
is it is some type of a alright, it is some type
of a material that has the same halachic status as as as
pottery, okay? So pottery and נתר nether vessels, this is so they
basically have what's their הלכה? halachah? טומאתן שווה. Tumatam shavah. They have
the same הלכה halachah for their טומאה, tumah, meaning what?
מטמאים ומיטמאים ומטמאים מאוירהן. metameim u-mitamei u-metameim me'avirahen. Now with the yod,
מיטמאים, mitameim, it's also like it would be מיטמאים mit'tameim because
it's like a התפעל hitpa'el reflexive. So they can receive טומאה tumah
and they can transfer טומאה tumah from their air. So if you
suspend a שרץ, sheretz, you know, a dead rodent that causes טומאה,
tumah, in their air space, so then it makes them טמא. tamei.
And if you suspend an apple in their air space, it makes
the apple טמא. tamei. So מיטמאים mitameim they become טמא tamei ומטמאים
u-metameim and transfer טומאה tumah in their air, that's the general rule
of
כלי חרס. kli cheres. ומיטמא מאחוריהן ואין מיטמא מגביהן. u-mitamei me'achoreihen ve-ein
mitamei migabeihen. Now this is a debated phrase what it means, you'll
see there's this huge תוספות Tosafot starting on the wide line and
going halfway down that try to that discusses what this means. What
רש"י Rashi says it means is the following: there are two different
words here, גב gav which means usually the back, and אחור achor
which means the back. So do they mean the same thing or
different things? So רש"י Rashi says they mean different things. If you
think about a קידוש Kiddush cup... Right, so you've got the receptacle
on the inside, but what you also have is you've got
the on the underside; if you pick it up and look on
the underside, there's also like a receptacle, not usually meant for keeping
anything, but it's a type of a receptacle, a base that has
inside of it a type of receptacle. רש"י Rashi says that's the
phrase אחוריים, Achora'im, okay, which means a receptacle essentially part of the
vessel that's really on the outside of the vessel,
not—well, in this case, the bottom, okay. The גב Gav just means
the normal back, okay? So according to רש"י, Rashi, the status of
כלי חרס, Kli Cheres, and תוספות Tosafos has a whole discussion whether
this is דאורייתא De'oraysa or דרבנן. Derabanan. The assumption is it's דרבנן.
Derabanan. The assumption is that biblically the only thing that's meaningful for
כלי חרס Kli Cheres is the normal receptacle part, the inside of
the cup to receive and to transfer טומאה. Tumah. But the underside
of this like the base and the receptacle part of the base,
which רש"י Rashi says is the אחוריים, Achora'im, there it can receive
טומאה Tumah through that as well, let's say at least rabbinically. The
assumption, by the way, is that if something receives טומאה, Tumah, it
can also transfer טומאה. Tumah. It's easier to become טמא Tamei than
to transfer טומאה, Tumah, okay? So רש"י Rashi says—yes, wait a minute,
or he has an alternate right, but he's okay with רש"י's Rashi
term. So that's מיטמאים מאחוריהם, Mitama'im Me'achoreihem, which means,
by the way, not only is this true biblically about the inner
receptacle, but even this outer base in the receptacle part, it can
also receive טומאה Tumah and therefore similarly it can also transfer טומאה,
Tumah, okay? So it really winds up having the same הלכה, Halacha,
but it would be rabbinic, which is why it's said separately. ואין
מיטמאים מגביהם: Ve'ein Mitama'im Migabeihem:
however,
if you touch something to the back of it, it cannot receive
טומאה. Tumah. It might, by the way, be able to transfer טומאה
Tumah if it touches the back of it, and again that would
be rabbinic. So the basic point according to רש"י Rashi is as—well,
everybody agrees the basic way it receives and transfers טומאה Tumah is
through—what do you call it?—is through the receptacle part, the inside, but
at least let's say rabbinically the
it can also do this same type of a thing by this
like the inside of the base, but the back side, certainly it
can't receive טומאה, Tumah, it might actually be able to transfer טומאה,
Tumah, that is not explicit in the גמרא. Gemara. That's the way
that רש"י Rashi reads this. So now how does תוספות Tosafos read
this? Just give me one second here as I give this
actual—so how does תוספות Tosafos read this? So תוספות Tosafos says that—just
hold on, just give me one second here. Okay, perfect. See if
it works. Okay, alright. So תוספות—so Tosafos תוספות Tosafos says that he
basically
likes רש"י's Rashi explanation, but he offers another one—three-quarters of this תוספות
Tosafos is defending
רש"י—and Rashi then he says,
one minute, let me just double-check: הרי פירש רש"י שהם מיטמאים מאחוריהם.
Harei peirash Rashi she-hem mitam'im me'achoreihem.
You know what? I'm going to bracket תוספות. Tosafos. It's a little
confusing; we'll leave ourselves with רש"י. Rashi. Okay, so that is the
basic הלכה, Halacha, that a כלי חרס Kli Cheres receives טומאה Tumah
when it's in the airspace and transfers טומאה Tumah in the airspace
and rabbinically also other parts about the back, maybe the maybe the
airspace of the base, maybe that also is a way to receive
and transfer טומאה. Tumah. But that's the basic הלכה Halacha of כלי
חרס. Kli Cheres. Then it goes on and says like this. So
the גמרא Gemara says the following: ושיריהן מטהרתו. Veshi'areihen Mitaharasan. The משנה
Mishnah ends by saying ושיריהן מטהרתו, Veshi'areihen Mitaharasan, okay, and the only
way you make the כלי חרס Kli Cheres טהור Tahor is not
by putting it in a מקווה Mikvah but by actually breaking it.
Alright, that's the הלכה Halacha of כלי חרס. Kli Cheres. So now
the גמרא Gemara comments the following way: כלי נתר וכלי חרס הוא
דטומאתן שוה. Kli neser ve-khli cheres hu de-tumatashen shavah. Fine,
it is this natron and pottery vessels that are in the same
category. Those are the only things that have the הלכה Halacha of
a כלי חרס. Kli Cheres. אבל מידי אחריני לא, Aval midi achrini
lo,
but not glassware. So again, we're at דף ז' עמוד א', Daf
Zayin Amud Aleph, about five lines down, and the basic point here
is that we said glassware is טמא Tamei because it's similar to
pottery, it's made out of sand, but now we're saying no, this
whole משנה Mishnah says the way pottery becomes טמא Tamei by the
airspace and it doesn't mention glassware. Presumably glassware has a different way
of becoming טמא. Tamei. So how do you explain why pottery is
not טמא Tamei when something is on the inner air space—why glass
is not טמא Tamei when it's in the inner airspace if glass
is based on the model of pottery? So now the גמרא Gemara
shifts gears. The גמרא Gemara says like this: אמרי, Amrei, you can
say or you should say, כיון דכי נשתברו יש להם תקנה, Keivan
de-khi nishtabru yesh lahem takanah, when glass breaks you can fix it.
You can actually blow the glass again, and there's a way to
like—nowadays glass is so cheap that we basically throw something out, but
it used to be that glassware was expensive. extremely expensive and you
could actually remake it the same way when you fashioned the glass.
I mean I don't know how, but something to do with like
you apply heat to it and you're able
to mend the crack. So therefore that's similar to what type of
a material? What type of material if it breaks can you use
heat to mend? Metal. Metal. So it says, ah, maybe it's not
like earthenware, maybe it's like metal. And so it says כיון דכי
נשתברו יש להם תקנה, keivan de-chi nishtabru yesh lahem takanah, שווינהו ככלי
מתכות, shavinhu k'cheli matachot, they made it like metal. We're going back
on what we said before. They're not like pottery, they're like metal.
Now תוספות Tosafot says that just because you can mend them wouldn't
have originally made us decide we're going to make them טמא. tamei.
Because fundamentally they're not like, they don't start being like metal. So
תוספות Tosafot says no, once we realized that they were fashioned like
out of sand and through heat and whatever, then we decided look,
this looks enough like pottery we're going to make it טמא. tamei.
But then little ironically we said okay, it's enough like pottery we're
going to make it טמא, tamei, but which category should we put
it in? We're going to put it in the metal category. So
it's a little funny. But in the end the גמרא Gemara now
is sort of switching sides and saying that even if it started
because it was similar to pottery, because of the idea that you
can mend it through the use of heat, we're going actually give
it more of the הלכה halachah category of metal. So we're going
to see whether the גמרא Gemara ends with this or not, but
that's where we are right now. Why? I don't even know why.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
What did you say? It's just like it doesn't get טמא.
tamei. Okay, the rabbinic enterprise is more than just making safeguards. סייג
seyag is actually I think more of a relatively smaller part of
the rabbinic enterprise. Part of the idea is
to extend these הלכתי halachic realities. So for example we were dealing
before about you can't carry in a כרמלית. karmelit. Is the reason
you can't carry in a כרמלית karmelit because you'll come to carry
in a רשות הרבים? reshut ha-rabim? Or is the reason you can't
carry in a כרמלית karmelit because carrying in a כרמלית karmelit is
close enough to carrying in a רשות הרבים? reshut ha-rabim? If carrying
in a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim is אסור, assur, carrying in a
כרמלית karmelit should also be אסור. assur. Even if you'll never in
your life carry in a רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. A lot of
rabbinic things don't have to be because of where it will lead
but because it's close enough to the biblical prohibited activity that it
as well should be made prohibited. That's another way you make a
buffer. Not just if you do this it'll come to do that,
but that we sort of extend that whole world of that whole
הלכתי halachic world. So that seems to be the point here. Yes.
I always thought initially that they would have considered glass with metal
because both of them have to be heated to high temperature and
maybe even melted and then poured into casts.
When you're originally making it.
When you're originally making it, yeah.
I mean when you make earthenware you also heat it to a
high temperature but you don't I guess fashion it that way.
No, you don't fashion it.
So maybe you're right. I mean תוספות Tosafot sort of tries to
hybridize them, but maybe in this shift of the גמרא Gemara it's
basically saying what you're saying. forget everything we said, it's not at
all like חרס, cheres, and maybe it's just like metal. But what
bothers תוספות Tosafot is it emphasizes fixing them and not making them.
But you're saying even the making them is similar.
Yeah, it could be. And glass has, glass by definition has metal
in it. Right, and it has the fragility of pottery.
That's another good point. Right. Made in both ways, yeah. Okay, yes.
I can't resist this, though. Sand and flame, fire, and how were
we created? Fire.
So there you go. Right.
Very good point. Very good point. Okay, so let's now, so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara does with this, if it's like earthenware
or not. So the גמרא Gemara says the following. It says, I
mean if it's like metal or not. אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata, says
גמרא, Gemara, okay, let's now try to argue it's metal. So by
the way that would explain why you can put it in a
מקוה, mikvah, it would explain why its טומאה tumah comes from the
touching of the outside or any side but not from being in
the air space.
But now there's one area that it doesn't fit the metal category.
אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata, says the גמרא, Gemara, יחזרו לטומאתן ישנה. yachzeru
le-tumatan yeshanah. It should go back to the old טומאה. tumah. What
does that mean?
ככלי מתכות, k'cheli matachot, like metal vessels. Where do we see that?
דתנן, dtan, we taught in the משנה. Mishnah. כלי מתכות, Klei matachot,
metal vessels, פשוטיהן ומקבליהן טמאים. pshuteihen u'mekableihen tme'im. They're even if they're
פשוט, pashut, they don't have a בית קיבול, beit kibul, receptacle. So
here's the general הלכה halachah about let's say earthenware only becomes, pottery
only, I should say earthenware, pottery only becomes טמא tamei if something
is in its airspace. Something like wood becomes טמא tamei even if
it's not in its airspace, even if you just touch טומאה tumah
to a wood spoon, but only if it does have a receptacle.
So if you think of like you've got a long wood spoon,
right, and you've got a
receptacle and it's got a spoon part to it, then even if
it touches the handle of the spoon. Okay, but but if it
has no receptacle, you've got a toothpick, you've got a fork let's
say. What? A board. A board, right, then it does not become
טמא. tamei. Now certain things by the way, talking about a board,
like a wood table that's totally flat, but it's used to hold
things is rabbinically
טמא. tamei. Okay, but but biblically not. And if something is completely
flat like it's a fork or whatever, or like a toothpick, a
whatever, a board. A stick, anyway those things do not become טמא.
tamei. That's wood; it needs to have a בית קיבול. beis kibul.
Now what do you call, now metal does not even need a
בית קיבול. beis kibul. Okay, metal is becomes טמא tamei even if
you've got let's say I don't know a needle. Okay, any metal
vessel becomes טמא tamei even without a receptor, alright? So let's take
a look at that and what that's going on here. Alright, so
it says like this, so it says where are we? So
כלי מתכות klei matechos metal פשוטיהן pshutehen ומקבליהן טמאים. umikablehen tme'im Their
פשוט pashut even without their having the receptacle, a simple you know
straight metal vessel like a needle and ומקבליהן umikablehen certainly if they
have things that have a בית קיבול beis kibul that have a
receptacle are טמא. tamei. So one הלכה halacha about metal is that
it does not need a receptacle. Then going on נשברו nishbiru if
they actually broke then נשברו טהרו nishbiru taharu they become טהור. tahor.
So by pottery the only way it can become טהור tahor is
if it breaks. Okay, by a metal vessel it becomes טהור tahor
either if you put it in the מקווה mikvah or if you
break it. Now what happens חזר ועשה מהן כלים chazar ve'asa mehem
kelim it broke and it became טהור tahor and then you went
back and you remade it into a vessel again. So then what's
going to be the הלכה? halacha? חזרו לטומאתן ישנה chasru letumasan yeshana
they go back to their old
טומאה. tumah. Alright, so here's the הלכה. halacha. Right, so it became
טמא, tamei, you broke it, and now you refashioned it, you went
out and you soldered it again, now it becomes טמא tamei again.
Now that's only דרבנן. derabbanan. Biblically once something is טהור tahor it's
טהור. tahor. You make it again it becomes another vessel, it can
become טמא tamei in the future but it doesn't restore its old
טומאה. tumah. But this is a special הלכה halacha we're saying by
metal vessels and we'll see why in a minute. ואילו לגבי כלי
זכוכית תנן ve'ilu legabei klei zechuchis tan but we know this is
not true by glassware, why? Because there we say כלי עץ וכלי
עור וכלי עצם klei etz veklei or veklei etzem if you have
a wooden vessel or you have a leather vessel like a sack
or you have a bone
vessel וכלי זכוכית פשוטיהן טהורין. veklei zechuchis pshutehen tehorin. So first of
all we have difference number one with a metal vessel, they do
not become טמא tamei if they are flat. All these things require
a בית קיבול. beis kibul. So like I said, the wooden spoon,
leather you would need to be a sack that has like something
to put something in something leather, a canteen, okay כלי עצם klei
etzem again like a bone spoon yes but a bone
made knife no and כלי זכוכית klei zechuchis and glass. So all
these things require receptacle. They become טמא tamei if you touch any
part of them but they require receptacle. So פשוטיהן טהורין pshutehen tehorin
number one and ומקבליהן umikablehen טמאים tme'im.
if they have a בית קיבול beis kibul if they do have
a receptacle then you touch any part of them they become טמא.
tamei. So נשברו טהרו nishbiru taharu they
become טהור. tahor. חזר ועשה מהן כלים chazar ve'asa mehem kelim if
you now refashion them after they break מקבלין טומאה מכאן ולהבא mekablin
tuma mikan ule'aba they can only become טמא tamei from here on
in but they do not restore their old טומאה. tumah. מכאן ולהבא
אין mikan ule'aba in from here on in yes למפרע לא lemafrea
lo not retroactively. So basically what this משנה mishnah makes clear is
that glassware really has a status
like wood or like bone ware. Okay, in the sense that all
the things are the same. Number one, we saw before you could
put it to the מקווה. mikvah. Number two, it can only become
טמא tamei if it has a receptacle. Number three, it can become
טמא tamei if you touch any part of it. All of this
is just like wood, okay? Number four, if it breaks and you
refashion it, it loses the old טומאה, tumah, it does not get
it back. So all of this is exactly like wood. There's only
a little problem, there's no logic to put it in the wood
category. So we tried putting it in the earthenware category but it
didn't fit. So now we're trying to put it in the metal
category. Well okay, but now we've got two anomalies which is not
like metal, which is more like things like wood. Number one it
needs a receptacle and number two the old טומאה tumah comes back
if you break it and refashion it. Why is that true if
you're putting it in the metal category? So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. Question?
Yes. A glass table, a flat glass table מקבל טומאה? mekabel tuma?
Not no, it's like according to it has to have a בית
קיבול. beis kibul. Now דרבנן derabbanan it could like oh like so
like wood presumably yes but דרבנן derabbanan not דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Right, okay
fine. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: so
why, so we're going to first focus on anomaly number one that
it its טומאה tumah does not come back unlike metal. So the
גמרא Gemara says here's the answer. טומאת כלי זכוכית דרבנן tumas klei
zechuchis derabbanan the whole glassware is דרבנן. derabbanan. וטומאה ישנה דרבנן ve'tuma
yeshana derabbanan the old טומאה tumah coming back is דרבנן. derabbanan. דאורייתא
de'oraisa once it goes away it never comes back. טומאה דאורייתא אחיתו
בה רבנן טומאה tuma de'oraisa achisu bah rabbanan tuma when did they
say that דרבנן derabbanan idea that the טומאה tumah will come back?
If we're dealing with a דאורייתא de'oraisa type of a vessel. טומאה
דרבנן tuma derabbanan by a דרבנן derabbanan טומאה, tumah, meaning something that's
only טמא tamei דרבנן, derabbanan, לא אחיתו לה רבנן. lo achisu le
rabbanan. The טומאה דרבנן Tumah d'Rabbanan they did not make it come
back. So they said, yeah, you're right. It is metal, like metal,
but it's Rabbinic. So we're not going to give it this extra
Rabbinic stringency that the טומאה Tumah comes back. Okay, let's deal now
with anomaly number two. פשוטיהן מהו ליטמא? Pshuteihen mahu litamei? Why doesn't
a simple straight glass vessel become טמא tamei even without a receptacle?
דהא פשוטי כלי מתכות דאורייתא נינהו. D'ha pshutei klei mateches d'Oraita ninhu.
So the גמרא Gemara says, because by metal, even if it doesn't
have a receptacle, it becomes טמא. tamei. So this is anomaly number
two, you're trying to make it like metal. Why does it need
a receptacle? So the גמרא Gemara says, no. עבדי רבנן היכירא. Avdi
Rabbanan heikera. The Rabbis again were saying so the Rabbis made a
distinction. Now why did they make a distinction? Here, biblically metal does
not need a receptacle, so glass should also not need to have
a receptacle. So it says, no, the Rabbis wanted to make one
law that didn't fit the category. Why? כי היכי דלא לשרפו עליה
תרומה וקדשים. Ki heichi d'lo lishrifu aleih Terumah v'Kodshim. So you shouldn't
come to burn תרומה Terumah and קדשים. Kodshim. So you should be
aware that it's only a Rabbinic problem, this glassware. You'll say, no,
this glassware can't really be a biblical issue. If it was a
biblical issue, then it wouldn't need to have a receptacle. So you
realize that it doesn't fit a category because you are so learned
in laws of טומאה וטהרה. Tumah v'Taharah. Exactly. Not only do you
know the הלכות halachos of glass, you're aware that those הלכות halachos
don't fit the metal category. And that signals you to remember that
this is not a normal הלכה, halacha, it's Rabbinic, and therefore you
will not come to burn תרומה וקדשים Terumah v'Kodshim that touch this
glassware that is טמא. tamei. You'll remember it's only Rabbinic. Now again,
we've now said that there are two ways it's unlike metal. Number
one is it doesn't restore the old טומאה. Tumah. Number two is
it does not need a receptacle. The easiest thing to do would
be to say it's like wood because the wood category fits nicely,
but there's no logic to say it's wood. So we're saying it's
like metal, we have two anomalies. One is we don't want to
apply another דרבנן d'Rabbanan on top of it, restoring the old טומאה.
Tumah. And number two is we make one thing not same so
you'll remember it's only Rabbinic. Now I should remind you that yesterday
we said all these things that they Rabbinically said were טמא tamei
to the point that you have to be שורף, soref, you have
to burn תרומה Terumah if it touches it. Right? Remember when we
did the stages of the גזירה gezeira and it gets to a
point that even though it's only Rabbinic, you burn תרומה. Terumah. So
the הלכה halacha is, the rule is there's no rule. Sometimes we
take Rabbinic categories and we say we're going to be so strict
on them that if they touch תרומה Terumah you even burn it.
Other times, like these glasswares, we're going to say we actually go
out of our way to do something different to make sure you
don't burn תרומה Terumah if it comes in contact with them. And
basically all the ראשונים Rishonim say there's no way of knowing why
we say one in one case, one in the other. Sometimes we're
strict, right, sometimes we're strict, sometimes we're not.
Okay, so all times you burn it, was that also for metal
and all that?
No, well, yes, but it was also these Rabbinic טומאות tumos about
בית הפרס Beit HaPras and ידיים Yadayim and all those cases. Okay.
So now we have explained that glass is like metal except for
two exceptions. Now one more explanation of this before we wrap up
glass. רב אשי אומר, Rav Ashi omer, top of טז עמוד ב.
Tet-Zayin amud Bet. רב אשי Rav Ashi says, לעולם לכלי חרס דמו.
L'olam l'klei cheres damu. Really they're like pottery.
ודקשיא לך, V'd'kashya lach, you're
bothered, לטמויי מגבן? litamei migaban? So what made you try to say
they shouldn't be like pottery? If they're like pottery, then why is
it even if you touch the outside of glass does it become
טמא? tamei? I've got an answer to that, he says. הואיל ותוכו
כברו. Hoil v'tocho k'baro. Okay, you remember that's actually a great phrase,
right? Remember when it spoke about, remember exactly, we had the whole
discussion about רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, and
who was allowed in the בית המדרש, Beit HaMidrash, whether the inside
is like the outside. Are you as frum on the inside as
you appear on the outside? So this idea it says, glass, actually
it's a nice idea, I want to be totally transparent with you,
right? So that's the idea, you're transparent. You're not hiding something on
the inside that's different than what you're saying on the outside. So
glass, תוכו כברו. tocho k'baro. If something is on the inside, you
see it on the outside. Glass is being totally transparent with you.
So if it's transparent glass, so he says, therefore, because it's hard
to see the distinction inside, outside, if you touch the outside of
the glass, it can also look like it's on the inside of
the glass because you can see it from the inside. So therefore
we didn't distinguish touching inside, touching outside by glass, and it really
is in the pottery category. But the idea of being on the
inside gets expanded because of the nature of glass.
We're not going to distinguish whether or not it is painted or
not, because then if it's painted you really can't see it as
much.
Presumably. Also, look, now the question is does that really answer everything?
Because it doesn't go back and deal with the other problems. We'd
still have to explain why can you put it in a מקווה
mikveh and go back and say that's a special case when it
got a hole and it was filled with metal. And why, for
example,
does
the old טומאה Tumah doesn't come back works, because the old טומאה
Tumah doesn't come back is just a הלכה halacha with metal. So
it fits that the old טומאה Tumah doesn't come back, it fits
that if they don't have a receptacle it doesn't become טמא. tamei.
So actually it does fit pretty closely the pottery category except this
idea of inside and outside and we're saying we're not going to
make a distinction. Okay, so that's the end of the pottery issue.
Really don't know which category to put it in. Is it metal
with certain anomalies or is it pottery with certain anomalies? Pottery the
anomalies are because there's no big because it's hard to see the
difference inside and outside. Metal certain anomalies in order just to make
for the purpose of making distinctions. Now this is really all into
טומאה וטהרה. Tumah Ve'taharah. I should say that it leads to interesting
discussions in the פוסקים Poskim now to become relevant. I do know
everybody that was coming from מוצאי שבת Motzai Shabbos and was expecting
that every דף Daf was going to be relevant to הלכות שבת,
Hilchos Shabbos, by now you realize that's not true. I mean we
had a couple of דפים Dapim that were very relevant, but not
for שבת, Shabbos, but sitting down and getting a haircut before מנחה
Mincha time or whatever. These two three דפים Dapim we're the middle
of of the eighteen things of שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel take
us in a world of טומאה וטהרה. Tumah Ve'taharah. You don't have
to worry by tomorrow we'll be done with it. Okay, but it
was a brief little digression into a world of טומאה וטהרה. Tumah
Ve'taharah. But here's a relevant point: Can you kosher glassware? Okay, so
why so some פוסקים Poskim want to say, ספרדים Sefardim versus אשכנזים,
Ashkenazim, right. So some פוסקים Poskim want to say,
ah let's see, glassware never gets discussed in the גמרא Gemara about
kashering, but it does get discussed somewhere else in the גמרא Gemara
about the status of glassware in this discussion of טומאה וטהרה. Tumah
Ve'taharah. Well let's see, if you say it's like pottery then you
can't kosher pottery. If you say it's like metal, you can kosher
metal. So maybe this discussion of how do you think of glassware
for טומאה וטהרה Tumah Ve'taharah should answer our question of could you
kosher it. Now a lot of פוסקים Poskim say very reasonably, what
the heck are you talking about? This is about some formalistic category
for purposes of טומאה וטהרה. Tumah Ve'taharah. The question if can you
kosher is a question about the physical characteristics of the thing and
to what degree does it absorb the food, what degree can you
extract it. Pottery the problem is is that the stuff can't come
out, but that's about the physical characteristic and that should not be...
you should not put glass in that category. And some פוסקים Poskim
even goes so far to say not only can you kosher glassware,
you don't even need to kosher it. Glassware doesn't even absorb any
of the taste, right?
And I remember you used to have a set of total set
of dishes for
פארעוו. Parve.
Right, so that exactly was true. There would used to be like
a generation or two ago, people would have, you know, glassware dishes
that they would not just glasses,
dishes they they would use both for מילכיגס Milchigs and for פליישיגס.
Fleishigs. Right, but that was פארעוו. Parve. But it used to be
some... oh I remember... right, right, some people so actually right, they
would use it for anything. Right, that it doesn't absorb. So anyway,
that is that... it's interesting though I just want to point out
to you, you know, that it shows it shows something about what
do you do when there isn't like an evidence in the גמרא
Gemara to answer your question. You go look for parallel cases, but
sometimes, you know, they're not really parallel, but some people will latch
on to a formalistic type of a category because at least the
גמרא Gemara is providing it. So this גמרא Gemara does by for
some פוסקים Poskim find this interesting for that הלכה. Halacha. Wait, Charlie
had his hand up, I give preference to people with their hands
up, yes.
Glass, common glass actually doesn't absorb anything. And if you look on
the internet on especially glass manufacturers, there are glasses that you can
buy glass glassware you can buy for industrial applications that do absorb
things and they are extremely expensive.
Interesting, very interesting.
So the common glassware
does not absorb
anything, yeah Bobby.
So are there פוסקים Poskim today, right, that you kosher... in other
words if you want to use glass from... believe me, I go
through this every year, from regular during the year to פסח. Pesach.
Yes, so for פסח Pesach they tend to be
pretty...
so depends who you ask but we tend to be stricter by
פסח Pesach than in general anyway. So you know you can ask
me פסח Pesach time. But no I'm serious, it depends who you
ask. If you really have like no option and it was a
minute before פסח Pesach and you had this whatever whatever, you'd get
different פסקים, Psakim, okay? But yeah, next question.
Does the fact that when you break glass and when you break
glass part of the glass is removed from the vessel? Yes. Even
if it's a little bit. Uh-huh, right. Does that have the fact
that you've lost something have any significance to this?
No. If it's broken, it's broken and it loses its טומאה. Tumah.
The fact that a piece fell off when it broke wouldn't really
matter. I mean that's not what it's about. It's about right, and
even
if you repair it and it isn't exactly what it was...
right, right, primarily it's the fact that it stops being functional. Okay,
so not every break but a break that stops it from being
so functional. Yes, Rivka.
I'm trying to understand the concept of טומאה Tumah if it disappears
when something is broken yet it can
reappear rabbinically. So does that mean it was lurking...
okay, so we'll talk... so we're about to actually get into the
next discussion is about a case of reappearing, so we'll see in
a minute what that's about.
Let me show you what you were saying before. So if you
hold that the glass is like the pottery, then we say glassware
can never be kosher, right? And some פוסקים Poskim say that, that
glassware can never be kosher.
But I don't
think
you
can
ever...
No one says it's like wood and apply, what do you mean?
So there are really only two options by כשר, kashering, metal and
wood, it's all the same.
This is all presumably about man-made glass. There are naturally occurring glasses,
obsidian, that are used for knives and extremely rarely other types of
כלים. keilei.
Interesting, I don't know.
Obsidian is like a volcanic rock?
It's a volcanic rock that is a naturally occurring glass, it's amorphous,
and it's been used for knives a lot. Cool.
Yes.
You said in the past that it was considered glass could be
used for everything. What is the present?
Well, I just think because in the past people, meaning the real
difference between the past and the present, besides that everybody is being
more מחמיר machmir these days, is also probably has to do with
general wealth. Meaning when people were poorer, I think פוסקים poskim were
more okay with the idea of just one set of dishes and
make it glass and so on. So nowadays you both have the
fact that people have more money as a general rule and two
sets of dishes is not a big issue, and that people in
general are more מחמיר. machmir. Right, but are there still פוסקים poskim
nowadays that say that glass doesn't absorb at all? Yes.
In other words, if you have a piece of glass, do you
consider that if it did have milk or meat on
it, you have to כשר kasher it between or whatever? Right, so
it depends who you ask. Some פוסקים poskim will say you don't
have to כשר. kasher. Okay, so let's go on. The גמרא Gemara
says like this, now, three lines from the top of ט"ז עמוד
ב'. Tes-Zayin Amud Bet.
שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shatach תיקן tikein כתובה kesubah לאשה. l'ishah.
So again, these are ancient תקנות takkanot before we get back to
שמאי Shammai and הלל. Hillel. שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shatach who
predated שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel said that a woman would have
a כתובה. kesubah. Now, what does this mean?
There's a whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara כתובות Kesubos whether כתובה
kesubah דאורייתא d'oraisa or דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Now, כתובה kesubah דאורייתא d'oraisa is
because the תורה Torah says, if a
man seduces a virgin, then כסף ישקול כמהר הבתולות, kesef yishkol k'mohar
habesulos, and then he has to pay money like the מהר הבתולות,
mohar habesulos, he pays the father the amount that the מהר mohar
that would go to virgins, which would be 50 שקל, shekel, which
we see from elsewhere, from a case of rape and so on,
50 שקל, shekel,
so 50 שקל. shekel.
Now 50 שקל shekel is 200 זוז, zuz, which is the amount
of the כתובה. kesubah. So that seems to be a source of
a biblical כתובה, kesubah, of the idea of כתובה kesubah in the
תורה. Torah.
But it's just an amount, right?
I'm getting to it, Michael. So and that's a debate in the
גמרא Gemara though whether כתובה kesubah is דאורייתא d'oraisa or דרבנן. d'rabbanan.
So what's the issue? I mean it says מהר הבתולות mohar habesulos
and that was 200 זוז, zuz, what's the issue? Well, part of
the issue is that in the תורה Torah that was money that
was paid upfront. The כתובה kesubah is paid at the end.
So is that the source of and the basis of our rabbinic
כתובה, kesubah, which is a money that would be paid on termination
of the marriage as opposed to the מהר, mohar, which was paid
upfront and it was actually paid to the father? So that's one
question. The other question is what function the מהר mohar did. Was
the מהר mohar a type of a bridal price and therefore that's
why it was paid to the father? Or was the מהר mohar
a type of a prepaid כתובה? kesubah? It was money that was
paid to the father to be held in escrow in case it
led to divorce or death, the husband died first and then the
wife would get that money. So the גמרא Gemara says it's not
clear and that's why there's a question how much is כתובה kesubah
based on the מהר mohar in the תורה. Torah. The גמרא Gemara
however says regardless the original practice was exactly that. That the groom
would take the 200 זוז zuz and put it upfront in escrow,
either to be held by the bride's father or to be held
by the bride, but it was paid upfront in escrow. So the
idea was that it would basically serve a type of an alimony
or type of a substitute for inheritance because if he died the
wife wouldn't inherit, the children would inherit, but it would be there
to support the woman once the husband was no longer around. However,
problem occurred, says the, this is in the תוספתא Tosefta it says
this. The problem is that if a husband decided he wanted to
divorce his wife and he divorced his wife before רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu
Gershom against her will and he just got bored with her, whatever,
he would just divorce her callously because there would be no consequence.
The כתובה kesubah money had already been paid. So there's nothing stopping
him to just one day waking up and decide he's bored with
his wife and divorce her. And the Rabbis did not like that.
They did not want this to be treated trivially. They said שלא
יהא קל בעיניו לגרשה, shelo yei kal b'einav l'garshah, it should not
just be easy to divorce, it should be something
that
requires serious thought and is only done when it really needs to
be done. And therefore they said we cannot have the כתובה kesubah
prepaid upfront. The כתובה kesubah has to be a payment at the
end so that any man will think twice before divorcing his wife
because wait a minute, if I divorce my wife I'm going to
have to liquidate my assets, I'm going to have to take money
out of my bank account, I don't want to do that. So
therefore he would hesitate and it would not be something that would
be overly hasty. And that is attributed to שמעון בן שטח. Shimon
ben Shatach. So it says when שמעון... Shimon... שמעון בן שטח *Shimon
ben Shetach* was מתקן כתובה *metaken kesuvah*, it does not mean the
whole institution. The whole institution might have started in the תורה *Torah*.
It certainly started beforehand as something in escrow, but he added the
aspect of the כתובה *kesuvah* that it would go from upfront to
the end שלא תהא קלה בעיניו לגרשה *shelo tehei kalla be'enav le'garshah*.
It should not be easy to divorce her. Okay, and that was
an additional purpose of the כתובה *kesuvah*, which meant that it would
be money that would be paid at the end and not upfront.
So that is the כתובה *kesuvah* associated with שמעון בן שטח *Shimon
ben Shetach*. We're not going to discuss that here, but I decided
I would give you the quick two-minute summary of that. Yes.
Doesn't mean the 18 things, right?
Just No, no. Well, in talking about the 18 things, we pulled
in earlier תקנות *takanos*. So we're still on earlier תקנות *takanos*. We
will get back to the 18 things, we are now on earlier
תקנות *takanos*. So that was one תקנה takanah *takana* he did. But
that would have been I think interesting to discuss, but the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is very focused on טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah *tuma ve'tahara*,
so it gets us back to the second תקנה takanah, *takana*. וגזר
טומאה tumah על כלי מתכות *Vegazar tuma al klei mateches*. And he
said metal becomes טמא tamei *tamei*. That's his second תקנה *takana*. That's
the one we're going to focus on. And the question's going to
be,
he didn't have to do that! Metal is טמא tamei *tamei* anyway,
it can become טמא tamei, *tamei*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is focused on. כלי מתכות דאורייתא
נינהו *Klei mateches d'oraisa ninhu*. That's biblical! דכתיב אך אשר את הזהב
ואת הכסף את הבדיל ואת העופרת את הנחשת ואת הברזל ואת הבדיל
ואת העופרת כל דבר אשר יבא באש תעבירו באש וטהר אך במי
נדה יתחטא *Dichsiv ach asher es hazahav ve'es hakesef, es habdil ve'es
ha'oferes, es hanocheshet ve'at habarzel ve'at habdil ve'at ha'oferet, kol davar asher
yavo ba'esh ta'aviru va'esh ve'taher ach b'mei nidda yischatta*. So this is
the vessels that they seized when they went to war against the
Midianites, and it said anything that's basically metal, you know, whether it's
gold or silver or, you know, iron or brass, whatever it is,
you you have to basically כשר *kasher* it if you want to
use it, and you have to sprinkle the ashes of the פרה
אדומה parah adumah, *parah adumah* on it if you want to make
it טהור tahor. *tahor*. So you see that metal becomes טמא tamei.
*tamei* and it needs to biblically become טהור tahor? *tahor*. Who needs
him to make metal טמא tamei. *tamei*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says לא נצרכה אלא ela, לטומאה ישנה *lo nitzrecha ela letuma yeshana*.
But we just said a minute ago that metal when you break
it loses its טומאה tumah. *tuma* and then when you refashion it
gets it back, that we said a minute ago was Rabbinic. Well,
who did that? שמעון בן שטח *Shimon ben Shetach* was the one
who instituted that Rabbinic rule. Why? What was the purpose of that?
דאמר רב Rav יהודה אמר רב מעשה בשלציון המלכה *Damar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav maiseh b'Sheltzion hamalka*. There's a story of שלציון *Sheltzion* the
queen, I believe the same as שלומציון *Shlomtzion*. שלומציון *Shlomtzion* is שלציון
*Sheltzion*, right, who was a חשמונאי *Chashmonai* from the בית חשמונאים *Beis
Chashmonaim*, a queen, her sister, right. שעשתה משתה לבנה *she'as'ta mishteh livna*.
She made a big feast, משתה *mishteh*, like a wedding feast for
her son. ונטמאו כל כליה *venitme'u kol keileha*, all of her כלים
*keilim* became טמא tamei. *tamei*, presumably somebody died during the feast and
therefore anything under the same roof became טמא tamei, *tamei*, all the
vessels became טמא tamei *tamei*. Now, of course we're also assuming that
we're in a world where people want to eat their חולין בטהרה
*chullin b'tahara*, right? Because that's basically a lot of what we've been
assuming right now, that everybody cares about טומאה tumah, וטהרה *tuma ve'tahara*.
And busy killing off whole cities. So what help, okay, so what
can they do with these vessels? Now, if somebody died, how long
is it going to take to get the vessels טהור tahor. *tahor*?
A week. We don't have a week! The wedding's tonight! So what
did they do? ושברתן *V'shavrasan*, she broke all of them, ונתנתן לצורף
*un'sanan l'tzoref*, she gave them to her what's called the metallurgist, what's
it called, the smelter, ודביקתן *ud'vichsan*, and he sort of melted, whatever,
you know,
he dissolved, not dissolved, what's the word, liqui-, I can't even come
up with the word, not exactly liqui-, what do you do when
you turn metal, you soften it, whatever he does, anyway, he soldered
it, ועשה מהן כלים חדשים *v'asa meihen keilim chadashim*. And he refashioned
them. So you broke them, you mended them, and now they're new
vessels. Great! Now we can use them! We don't have to wait
the whole week! Perfect solution! Okay,
ואמרו חכמים *v'omru chachamim*, and the rabbis said, sorry, יחזרו לטומאתם הישנה
*yachzeru letumasam hayeshana*, they get back to their old טומאה tumah. *tuma*.
Okay, now.
So they made the decree that day.
Right. Now, you know, you might have thought they might have wanted
to wait a little after till the queen was done with her
wedding feast. All right.
But wasn't her brother the main sage left?
Yeah, yeah. So anyway, maybe they did it a day later. I
don't know. Anyway, מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*? Now why did they make
this גזירה gezeirah *gezeira*? משום גדר מי חטאת נהגו בה *Mishum geder
mei chatas nahagu bah*. Because if you do this, nobody is ever
going to bother using, you know, having the ashes of the פרה
אדומה *parah adumah*. I mean, for a person you'll need it, but
for vessels you'll never bother. You'll say why wait a week, just
break the vessels and mend them. So they were afraid that that
would undermine the entire institution, as it were, of the ashes of
the פרה אדומה *parah adumah*, that people are always doing this workaround.
You're not bothered, at least you need it for people. Exactly. All
right. I don't know what to say. Anyway, so they were concerned
about that. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute. הני למאן דאמר
leman de'amar, לא לכל הטומאות אמרו amru, *Hani leman de'amar lo lechol
hatumos amru*. That's good if you say that when they said it
reverts, the old טומאה *tuma* reverts, that's only if it's the טומאה
*tuma* of not all טומאות tumos, *tumos*, only a טומאה *tuma* of
טומאת מת tumas meis. *tumas meis*, then the תקנה *takana* is not
to use this as a workaround for the ashes of פרה אדומה
*parah adumah*. So we said it only by טומאת מת tumas meis,
*tumas meis*, not all טומאות tumos. *tumos*. אלא לטומאה *Ela letuma*. אלא
לטומאת מת בלבד, it only applies to טומאת מת. tumas meis. אמרו,
אלא, so if you say they only said it for טומאת מת,
tumas meis? שפיר, shapir, then that makes sense, that's what it's about,
not to be a workaround for
טומאת מת. tumas meis אלא למאן דאמר לכל הטומאות אמרו, ela leman
de'amar lekhol hatumos amru, but if they said it for all טומאות,
tumos? מאי איכא למימר, mai ikka l'meimar, so why did you do
why did you make this תקנה that you can't break it and
re-mend it? It can't be about not doing a workaround for פרה
אדומה, then it would be limited to טומאת המת. tumas hameis. So
there's gotta be some other reason why you're saying that the old
טומאה gets restored if it applies to all טומאות. tumos So אמר
אביי גזירה שמא לא ישברנו בכדי טהרתו, Amar Abaye gezeirah shema lo
yishvirenu bikhdei taharaso,
because you're doing all of these tricks, you know, you might not
do the tricks sufficiently. You're going to break it and it'll be
a little break, because you know, who wants to do a big
break? Then it's gonna take more work to mend, and then it's
gonna look uglier after it's mended. So once you feel you've got
this out, oh, just break it and get it mended, you're gonna
make a very minor break, and it won't really become טהור. tahor
So we can't let you do this.
So
רבא אמר גזירה שמא יאמרו טבילה בת יומא עלתה לה. Rava amar
gezeirah shema yomru tevilah bas yoma olah lah. So רבא Rava said
that no, there's another concern. The concern is that people will see
that this became טמא today, then they'll see later today you're using
it. So what will a normal person think if it's not טומאת
מת? tumas meis They'll think you took it to the מקוה. mikvah.
That's why you're using it. But one minute, what did we learn?
You take something טמא to the מקוה, mikvah, when does it become
טהור? At night. At night. So they'll see you're using it the
same day. So they'll come to think that once you take something
to the מקוה, mikvah, you can use it that day, because they'll
assume that's what you did, you took it to the מקוה. mikvah.
That only applies to metal vessels and those kinds of things?
Well, metal vessels presumably were the easiest to fix. So those were
the ones, Mike, was a good question, why not say it by
all vessels? Presumably the answer is that other vessels were a lot
harder to fix. You know, metal you can solder and other types
of things, so there there was more of a concern that people
would be doing this type of stuff. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What difference is there between whether it's about,
you know, if it's about טומאת מת tumas meis? then there's an
obvious difference, is it only by טומאת מת tumas meis. or other
טומאות? tumos But if it's about אביי ורבא, Abaye veRava, אביי Abaye
says you won't break it well enough, and רבא Rava says the
problem is what people will say. What's
the נפקא מינא? nafkamina? איכא בינייהו דצרפיהו מרציי. ikka beinaihu ditzratfinhu martzei.
The difference is is whether you you know broke it into a
lot of little pieces. That's what רש"י Rashi says it means. So
which side would that work for? So רש"י Rashi has two answers.
One answer is if the concern is you won't break it well
enough, if you really break it into a lot of pieces, then
then we won't be concerned. If it's a little break and you
basically retained its structural integrity, then we'll say it gets back its
טומאה. You could also understand that, because then we'll say since it
retains its structural integrity, it still has, you know, like as רי"ף
Riff said, it's got the old טומאות still lurking there because it's
still basically the vessel. If you break it into a lot of
little pieces, then then there's no concern you won't break it well
enough, and then it does not restore. However, if it's what people
will say, people will still see earlier today it was טמא, later
today you're using it, they'll make the mistake. That's one way of
saying it. רש"י Rashi suggests the exact opposite read as well, which
is if it's afraid about what people will say, if you broke
it into a lot of little pieces and then you mended it,
it will be very obvious that it's a mended vessel. They'll see
like all the lines that it was soldered and put back together.
And there there's no concern that people will confuse what happened. So
anyway, two versions about which way this breaks down. I should make
one other point about this, about when the גמרא Gemara says does
it apply to all טומאות or just טומאת מת? tumas meis The
גמרא Gemara says according to the one that says it applies to
just טומאת מת. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, it's about
eight lines down in the narrow lines, where it says למאן דאמר,
רש"י Rashi says לא ידענא היכא. lo yadana heikha. I don't know
where this is, where this debate is that somebody says only טומאת
מת and somebody says it applies to everything. Now if you take
a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot actually says actually it's in
a תוספתא. Tosefta. הניחא למאן דאמר לכל הטומאות אמרו. Hani kha leman
de'amar lekhol hatumos amru. תוספות Tosafot says רבן גמליאל סבירא ליה הכי
בתוספתא דכלים Rabban Gamliel sevirah lei hakhi beTosefta deKeilim and some actually
switch it that it's whatever, תוספתא דכלים Tosefta deKeilim or some say
מסכת כלים. Masekhet Keilim. Anyway so anyway but תוספות Tosafot tries to
identify where it is. But there are places where רש"י Rashi says
I don't know what this is referring to. The גמרא refers to
something else and if you take a look, you know the גליון
הש"ס Gilyon HaShas points you to the רש"י Rashi in ברכות Berakhot
that said that and that and there the גליון הש"ס Gilyon HaShas
lists every, there's רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger lists every place
in ש"ס Shas where רש"י Rashi says I don't know what this
is referring to. Like the גמרא makes a reference and רש"י Rashi
can't identify the reference. And a lot of times תוספות Tosafot tries
to identify the reference and sometimes even תוספות Tosafot can't identify the
reference. Okay, anyway moving on. Now the גמרא says like this: ואידך
מאי? ve'idakh mai? So back to the י"ח דבר. yud-ches davar. Okay,
we had a whole little digression about other things that were mentioned,
הלל ושמאי מיסו Hillel veShammai meisu and גזירת שמעון בן שטח, gezeiras
Shimon ben Shetach, all these other early גזירות, gezeiros, now we're back
to the 18. So we had listed I forget how many you
can go back and count at the end but we have listed
about six things of שמאי והלל Shammai veHillel about ידיים... yadayim... here
you want to let me try to get my phone off, try
to count them at the top. What were the six things here?
Oh my god I can't do this. Why? Okay. So it says
like this: if you eat אוכל ראשון ochel rishon and אוכל שני,
ochel sheini, that might count as two, you become טמא. If you
drink משקין טמאין, mashkin tmein, you become טמא. If you go ראשו
ורובו במים שאובים, rosho v'rubo b'mayim shu'uvim, like the bath after the
מקוה, mikvah, or you take a shower, that's five, right? Those things
you become a שני. sheini. A ספר תורה, sefer Torah, hands are
always a שני. sheini.
And
food and vessels that touch משקין, mashkin, that משקין mashkin get upgraded
to become a ראשון rishon and the food and vessels become a
שני. sheini. That's either like eight or nine, okay, if you count
food and vessels as separate. So we have already eight or nine.
We need to get about another nine or ten. So what are
they for the eighteen? So let's take a look. So the גמרא
says like this, where are we? Two dots, middle of ט"ז עמוד
ב'. tet-zayin amud bet. והאידך מאי היא, v'ha'idach mai hee, what are
the other ones? דתנן, d'tnan, we taught in the משנה. mishna. המניח
כלים תחת הצינור לקבל בהן מי גשמים. hamaniach keilim tachat hatzinor l'kabel
bahen mei geshamim.
You put vessels under a drain pipe in order to collect the
drain water. Now this is going to be the question, remember water,
if it comes in contact with food, with the fruits and vegetables,
whatever, makes it susceptible to become טמא. But only if you want
it to become in contact with it, or if... oh, I'm sorry
one minute, this is not about susceptible, hold on one second, let
me just... one second... let me just... one
second... no,
no, no, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. This is not about, I jumped
ahead, this is not about where it can mix with the other
case. This is not about making it susceptible, this is about a
different הלכה. halacha. We've seen both of these הלכות halachot before. I
got... but anyway, we saw the הלכה halacha before about making things
susceptible, but we also saw the הלכה halacha before about how much
drawn water invalidates a מקוה. mikvah. Okay, so this is the issue
about the drawn water invalidating a מקוה. mikvah. Now if you draw...
the simple case of drawn water is, you go and you draw
the water from the well and you pour it into the מקוה.
mikvah. But there is another case in the משניות mishnayot in מקואות
Mikvaot is, if the very fact that the water is collected in
a vessel, even if you didn't carry it, defines the water as
drawn water. So it rains into a vessel, the vessel then breaks,
and the water spills into a מקוה, mikvah, that's considered drawn water
because it was held within a vessel. But only if you wanted
it in the vessel. If you wanted it in the vessel, that's
like you drew it by the vessel, even if you did no
physical act. So you got it? The question is, rain water's going
to fall into this vessel, you're not going to touch it, then
it's going to break and fall into a מקוה. mikvah. Is it
drawn water or not? And the answer is, did you want the
rain water to go into this vessel?
Just thinking about, let's say you just had an open pit, which
you consider as a מקוה, mikvah, you want the rain water to
go in there.
Yeah, but that's not a vessel. The whole idea of a vessel
is that a vessel is the type of thing you would draw
with. So wanting it to go into the vessel is like you
drew it with the vessel. So that's the question. When it goes
in, the rain falls into it, did you want it in the
vessel or not? Stone could be a... could be a vessel...
right... not a... I suppose...
yeah, we're actually going to see that here in a minute. Right,
right, right. But we're going to see it here in a minute.
המניח כלים תחת הצינור לקבל בהן מי
גשמים. hamaniach keilim tachat hatzinor l'kabel bahen mei geshamim. So you put
vessels under the drain pipe in order to catch the rain water.
Okay. אחד כלים גדולים
ואחד
כלים קטנים, echad keilim gedolim v'echad keilim ktanim, whether they're big or
small vessels. Why that should matter? תוספות Tosafot says because some vessels
are so big that they're לא מקבל טומאה. lo mikabel tumah. If
you have like a huge, you know,
thing like the size of, I don't know, a refrigerator or something,
it might be so big that you don't... wouldn't ordinarily be able
to carry it when it is full. Actually, the size is the
same size of מקוה, mikvah, forty סאה. se'ah. Then it's so big,
it's normally not considered a vessel to be מקבל טומאה. mikabel tumah.
But the point the גמרא is making here, even though it can't
be מקבל טומאה, mikabel tumah, it's still enough of a vessel to
define the rain water as drawn. Okay. It's actually an interesting question
in general by halachic categories. When I say something this big is
no longer מקבל טומאה, mikabel tumah, I could say it two ways.
Yes, it's a vessel, but within the laws of being מקבל טומאה,
mikabel tumah, it can't be מקבל טומאה. mikabel tumah. Or I say,
no, the reason it's not מקבל טומאה mikabel tumah is when it's
so big, it stops being considered a vessel. So that's the חידוש
chiddush here. It still is a vessel. It's not מקבל טומאה, mikabel
tumah, but it's still a vessel. And therefore, if rain water falls
into it, it's going to be considered drawn rain water. So whether
it's big, whether it's small, ואפילו כלי אבנים v'afilu klei avanim and
here's another category of vessels that are not מקבל טומאה: mikabel tumah:
stone, like David said, וכלי אדמה v'klei adamah or earthenware that's not
pottery, that's not been, like, fired in a kiln, וכלי גללים v'klei
glalim or which is basically made out of, out of dung. They
would make vessels out of dried dung. Crap. Yes, all these things.
רש"י Rashi here says it means marble, but usually it's understood to
be dung. Anyway, all these things are not מקבל טומאה, mikabel tumah,
but they're still vessels. And that's the point. Even though they're not
מקבל טומאה, mikabel tumah, they're vessels and if rain water falls in
it, it becomes like drawn rain water. So all these cases, פוסלין
את המקוה. poslin et hamikvah. They and then the water goes from
the vessels into a מקוה, mikvah, it invalidates a מקוה mikvah if
it went in before there was forty סאה. se'ah. אחד המניח, echad
hamaniach, whether you put it there intentionally where obviously you wanted it
to fill up, ואחד השוכח, v'echad hashochei'ach, even if you forgot it
there, you did not intentionally plan for it to fill up, you
forgot... and then you forgot, and then it rained later, okay? דברי
בית שמאי. divrei Beit Shammai. That's what בית שמאי Beit Shammai says.
ובית הלל מטהרין בשוכח. u'veit Hillel metaharin b'shocheach. הלל Hillel still says
as if you put it there and then you forgot about it,
and you weren't intending it, then it does not make the water
drawn water. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says, נמנו ורבו בית שמאי על בית הלל, nimnu ve'rabu Beit
Shammai al Beit Hillel, they took a vote and that time בית
שמאי Beit Shammai was more than בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית
שמאי Beit Shammai won out. So but we know that they took
a vote in the י"ח דבר, yud chet davar, in the things
that happened in this attic and this second story. So therefore this
is from the eighteen things that בית שמאי Beit Shammai won out.
It says even if you leave the vessels they it becomes like
drawn water, even if you forgot them. Now within this debate we
make the following sort of qualifications. ומודים בית שמאי בשוכח בחצר שהוא
טהור. U'modim Beit Shammai b'shocheach b'chatzer shehu tahor. בית שמאי Beit Shammai
agrees that when you forget it in the what do you call
it, in the courtyard it is טהור. What does that mean? Meaning
if it's in the middle of the yard, it's not right there
under the drainpipe, then he says fine. You didn't put it there
intentionally to collect rainwater, you forgot it, and you forgot it in
a place where normally people aren't putting it there to collect rainwater,
it's in the middle of the yard. But if you forgot it
under the drainpipe, no way. Then I'm going to say that looks
too close to the case of intentionally putting it there and that's
where I'm going to say it's a problem. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar
Rabbi Yosi, עדיין מחלוקת במקומה עומדת. adayin machloket bimkomah omedet. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi said, you know what, it's not true. בית שמאי Beit
Shammai did not win out over בית הלל. Beit Hillel. The debate
remains. So according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, it cannot be one
of the eighteen things, which we'll get back to. Now one more
qualification and then we're going to get back to the eighteen things.
אמר רב משרשיא דבי רב אמרי, Amar Rav Mesharshiya d'vei Rav amri,
the house of רב they say, הכל מודין שכשניחה בשעת קישור עבים
טמאים. hakol modin shekshenichah b'sha'at kishur avim temeyim. Everybody agrees that if
you put it under the drainpipe when it was cloudy out and
about to rain and then you forgot about it, you can't say
oh it wasn't intentional or whatever. Even בית הלל Beit Hillel would
agree it's like it was intentional. בשעת פיזור עבים, B'sha'at pizur avim,
if you put it under the drainpipe when there were no clouds
in the sky and then you forgot about them, everybody agrees that
that's not like it's drawn. Of course it raises questions, why are
you putting it under the pipes if not to collect the rainwater
when it does rain? But the point might be since when you
put it under the pipes it wasn't about to rain and when
it had rained you had forgotten about it, so when it actually
filled with water, it's not like you were filling it with water.
You understand, it's not enough that you put it there with that
intention. What we have to what we're basically saying is because you
intended it, it's like you filled it with water. So here, if
you put it there when it wasn't about to rain and three
days later it rained and you weren't thinking about it, then when
it was filling with water it's not like you drew the water.
And everybody would agree that that is not a problem. So
לא נחלקו אלא שהניח בשעת קישור עבים. lo necheleku ela sheheneach b'sha'at
kishur avim. Here's what happened. You put it under the drainpipe when
it was cloudy out and it was about to
rain, then ונתפזרו, v'nitpazru, then the clouds
separated, וחזרו ונתקשרו, v'chasru v'nitkashru, and then they got dark again and
then it rained. So is that because initially you were hoping it
to fill with water but then you forgot about it and there
was actually a break in the experience and then it rained afterwards,
is that like at that time like it was part of the
same process and like you were intentionally filling it up? מר סבר
בטלה מחשבתו, Mar savar batlah machashavto, the first opinion of בית הלל
Beit Hillel holds forget it, you know there was a break, the
clouds separated, so even though you wanted to fill at that time
you had forgotten and it's not part of the same process and
it's not like you drew it. ומר סבר לא בטלה מחשבתו, U'mar
savar lo batlah machashavto, no, it's still your מחשבה machshava is still
seen as continuous and therefore since it was put with that intent
and it was about to rain and then it did rain even
though there was a break, it's like you filled it. That's the
debate, again between בית שמאי ובית הלל, Beit Shammai u'Veit Hillel, but
the point being it's not enough that you wanted it when you
put it there, it has to be seen as then when it
did rain it's like you filled it so there has to be
some type of a continuity of the process. Now the גמרא says
the following.
ולרבי יוסי דאמר מחלוקת עדיין במקומה עומדת, U'leRabbi Yosi d'amar machloket adayin
bimkomah omedet, according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that says the debate
still remains, בית הלל Beit Hillel did not sort of concede to
בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, was not outvoted by בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
so בצרי להו, batzri lehu, so we have one fewer because we're
trying to get up to eighteen. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק,
amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אף בנות כותים נדות מעריסתן בו ביום
גזרו. af bnot kutim niddot me'arisatan bo bayom gazru. So this is,
for those that remember נידה, niddah, a גזירה that the כותים, Kutim,
Samaritans, are הלכתית halachically Jewish, גרי אמת, geirei emet, but but they're
not they don't follow the same rabbinic rules or rabbinic interpretation about
laws of נידה. niddah. So the Rabbis say a woman could become
a נידה niddah even if she bleeds one day old woman, baby.
But the כותים Kutim say no, only when she reaches like the
age of maturity. So because they were afraid that they did not
follow the same laws and they might have said that they were
טהור when they were טמא, the Rabbis said we're going to treat
all of כותים Kutim women, even one-day-old infants, as טמא from the
moment they're born. Okay? And that was a תקנה, a debate of
שמאי והלל, Shammai v'Hillel, and that was a case where שמאי Shammai
voted and outruled הלל, Hillel, so that gives us yet one more
of the eighteen. things that בו ביום גזרו. bo bayom gazru. That
day that they took the vote, this was one of the eighteen
things and we will continue, let's stop here, we'll continue tomorrow to
see to continue to get to the four. The
next of the eighteen גזירות gezeirot that was enacted בו ביום bo
bayom is the law regarding בציר. batzir. This refers to the harvesting
of grapes. There is a rule in טומאה וטהרה that for a
food to become susceptible to טומאה, it must first be moistened by
one of the ז׳ משקין, zayin mashkin, the seven liquids. However, this
only applies if the moisture comes לרצון, l'ratzon, meaning with the owner's
approval. When grapes are harvested, sometimes they get crushed and juice comes
out. הלל Hillel held that this is not לרצון, l'ratzon, because the
person is not interested in this small amount of juice that is
released during the harvesting process. שמאי, Shammai, on the other hand, held
that it is לרצון. l'ratzon. They took a vote on this, and
the opinion of שמאי Shammai prevailed over the opinion of הלל. Hillel.
As a result, this became one of the eighteen גזירות, gezeirot, that
the juice of the בציר batzir makes the grapes susceptible to טומאה.